the branch chain amino acids Lucine
isoline and veine are essential amino
acids but can we overdo it check out the
[Music]
video diabetes isn't just about the
amount of body fat but the distribution
of body fat check out these
cross-sections of two different thighs
from two different patients this is an
MRI so the fat shows up as white and the
black is the thigh muscle at first
glance it looks like the one in the
bottom has more fat that's the
subcutaneous fat Under the Skin but if
you look at the top one see how their
muscle is more marbled in the Middle
with fat those those white streaks
that's not Grizzle that's fat like one
of those really fatty Japanese beef
steaks that's the fat infiltrating into
the muscle colored in red there the
green is the fat between your muscles
and then the yellow is the fat outside
of the muscles under the skin and if you
add up all three types both of those
thighs actually have the same amount of
fat just distributed differently and
that seems to be the critical factor in
terms of determining insulin resistance
the cause of type 2 diabetes the
subcutaneous adapost tissue the the fat
right under the skin was not associated
with insulin resistance so it's
healthier to have this thum
is it possible a more plant-based diet
also affects a more healthier
distribution of fat we didn't know until
now the effect of a vegetarian versus
conventional diabetic diet on thi fat
distribution in subjects with type 2
diabetes researchers decided to put it
to the test 74 diabets were randomly
assigned to either follow a vegetarian
diet or conventional diabetic diet both
diets were calorie restricted down to
the same number of calories the
vegetarian diet was also eggree and
dairy limited to a Max of a one serving
of low-fat yogurt a day and the
reduction in the more benign
subcutaneous fat was comparable about
the same in both groups but the more
dangerous fat the fat lodged inside the
muscle itself was reduced only in
response to the more plant-based eye so
even on the same number of calories
there can be a healthier weight loss on
a more plant-based diet those eating
strictly plant-based also have lower
levels of fat stuck inside the
individual muscle fibers themselves
what's called intramyocellular lipid
which may help explain why vegans in
particular are often found to have the
lowest odds of diabetes and it's not
just because they're Slimmer even if you
match subjects pound for pound there's
significantly less fat inside the muscle
cells of vegans compared to omnivores as
measured in one of their calf muscles
which is a good thing since storing fat
in muscle cells Maybe one of the primary
causes of insulin resistance which is
what's behind both pre-diabetes and type
2 diabetes whereas if you put someone on
a high fat diet in just a single week
the fat in their muscle cells shoots up
54% and go on a high protein diet and
you may undermine one of the principal
benefits of weight loss eliminating the
weight loss induced Improvement in
insulin action the Improvement in
insulin resistance obese individuals
were put on a calorie restricted diet
less than 1,400 calories a day until
they lost 10% of their body weight half
we're getting more of a regular protein
intake 73 g a day and the other half a
higher protein diet now normally you
lose 10% of your body weight and your
insulin resistance improves that's why
it's so critical for obese type 2
diabetics to lose weight but the
beneficial effect of 10% weight loss was
eliminated by the high protein intake
those extra 32 gram of protein a day
abolished the weight loss benefit the
failure to improve insulin sensitivity
in the high protein weight loss group is
clinically important because it reflects
a failure to improve a major cause and
effect mechanism involved in the
development of type 2 diabetes in
summary they concluded they demonstrated
that the protein content of a weight
loss diet can have profound effects on
metabolic function all protein any kind
of protein if you split it up between
animal versus plant protein following
people over time animal protein intake
is associated with an increased risk of
diabetes in most studies whereas plant
protein intake appears to have either a
neutral or protective association with
diabetes yeah but those were just
observational studies people who eat
lots of animal protein might have lots
of unhealthy behaviors but you see the
same thing in randomized controlled
Interventional trials where you can
improve blood sugar control just by
replacing sources of animal protein with
plant protein we think it may be the
branch chain amino acids concentrated in
animal protein higher levels in the
bloodstream are associated with obesity
and development of insulin resistance we
may be able to drop our Levels by
sticking to plant proteins but you don't
know if that has metabolic effects until
you put it to the
test I hate it when titles ruin the
suspense but indeed decreased
consumption of Branch chain amino acids
improves metabolic Health they
demonstrate that a moderate reduction in
protein intake rapidly improves
metabolic Health improving blood sugar
control while also decreasing BMI and
body fat check this out the protein
restricted group was eating literally
hundreds more calories per day
significantly more calories than the
control group so they should have gained
weight right but no they lost weight
after about a month and a half they were
eating more calories but lost more
weight about five pounds more than the
control group eating fewer calories and
this protein restriction they were just
having people eat the recommended amount
of protein a day so that's about 56 gram
a day so they should have just called
that the normal protein group or or or
the the recommended protein group and
the group that was eating more typical
American protein levels and suffering
because cost of it the excess protein
group and as a bonus just sticking to
the recommended protein intake doubled
the levels of a prolongevity hormone
called fgf21 but that's for another
video
[Music]